<title>S2 Client Protocol</title>
<para>
  This protocol, initially implemented for
  <ulink url="http://www.livejournal.com/">LiveJournal.com</ulink> but applicable
  elsewhere, provides a machine-friendly interface to an S2 system on a
  remote server.
</para>
<para>
  The protocol is just HTTP. You can implement it using any suitable HTTP
  library, including the Perl LWP library.
</para>
<section id="&s2.idroot;csp.general">
  <title>General Rules</title>
  <para>
    A new <parameter>Content-type</parameter> value is introduced for S2 layers, named
    <literal>application/x-danga-s2-layer</literal>. This is used both in server
    responses and client layer uploads.
  </para>
  <section id="&s2.idroot;csp.general.request">
    <title>Requests</title>
    <para>
      When making a request to the S2 interface, you can authenticate with the
      remote server using HTTP Digest authentication<footnote id="&s2.idroot;csp.general.ftn.digest_auth">
         <simpara>
           Refer to <ulink url="http://www.faqs.org/rfcs/rfc2617.html">RFC 2617</ulink>
           for more information.
         </simpara>
      </footnote>
      or some site-specific authentication method. On LiveJournal.com, session
      cookies are supported.
    </para><para>
      The request URL will vary between applications. On LiveJournal it can be
      found at <systemitem class="systemname">/interface/s2</systemitem>.
      </para>
      <para>An example uploading client named <filename>s2up.pl</filename> for
      the protocol, written in perl using LWP, is in the
      SVN <ulink url="http://code.sixapart.com/svn/s2/trunk/tools/s2up.pl">repository</ulink>.</para>
    <para>The same URL is used for both retrieval and updating; the method used
      defines the action the server will take. On LiveJournal, that URL will be
      <systemitem class="systemname">/interface/s2/<replaceable>layerid</replaceable></systemitem>.
      How you find the correct layerid is outside the scope of this specification.</para>
  </section>
  <section id="&s2.idroot;csp.general.response">
    <title>Responses</title>
    <para>
      When parsing response bodies, consider only ASCII character 10 (newline, \n)
      to indicate a newline. Disregard any occurrences of ASCII 13 (carriage return, \r).
    </para><para>
      Error responses have a HTTP error code and a plain text
      response body. This will contain a short error message, then a newline,
      then a longer error message also followed by a newline, and optionally
      other data which you may wish to display.
    </para><para>
      If the response is not in the expected format (i.e. content-type does not
      indicate a plain text response) clients should simply explain that the
      server has returned an invalid response and that this may be temporary
      or might be due to an incorrect URL. Even in the case of an unparsable body,
      the HTTP response code can be used to infer the nature of the error.
    </para><para>
      You should be prepared to accept any HTTP response code and treat it as
      the HTTP spec advises. This includes the redirection codes. You are
      advised to use a full HTTP library, which is available for most
      languages, to make your requests rather than hacking up flakey HTTP code
      which assumes everything will always work in a particular way.
    </para><para>
      An exception to this rule is that the <returnvalue>403 Forbidden</returnvalue>
      response is defined in HTTP to indicate that "authentication will not help".
      This protocol also allows for it to describe the condition where
      authentication credentials are given but the given account has no access
      to whatever was requested. This slight quirk is made under the assumption
      many clients for this protocol will be non-interactive and launched as tools
      from text editors, and prompting for alternative credentials would be impossible.</para>
  </section>
</section>
<section id="&s2.idroot;csp.download">
  <title>Retrieve Layer Source</title>
  <para>
    In order to get the S2 source of a layer for local editing, a simple GET
    request is sufficient:
  </para>
    
<programlisting>GET /interface/s2/1 HTTP/1.1
Host: www.livejournal.com
Accept: application/x-danga-s2-layer</programlisting>

  <para>
    In addition to the basic header shown above, digest
    authentication<footnoteref linkend='&s2.idroot;csp.general.ftn.digest_auth'/> can
    be used.
           Anonymous requests are allowed, but the server may respond with 
           <returnvalue>401 Unauthorized</returnvalue>, describing the standard HTTP
    authentication methods supported. Some servers, as described above, may
    implement <quote>special</quote> authentication methods,
    such as LiveJournal supporting website session cookies. These are not
    described (in a machine-readable way, at least) in the Unauthorized response.
  </para>
  <para>
    Client authors are <emphasis>strongly advised</emphasis> to send the
    <parameter>Accept</parameter> header, as in the future other formats
    may be supported and the server will be able to see which
    format you are expecting and either honor your request or return the
    response <returnvalue>Unacceptable</returnvalue> if S2 layer source
    as we know it now is unavailable.
  </para>
  <para>
    If the response is an error, the response body will contain a short error
    followed by details of the error, plus optionally further error lines 
    which you may wish to display if they are present. The HTTP response code 
    will give you some idea of the nature of the error.
  </para>
  <para>
    If the response is successful (response code is 200 OK), and the
    <parameter>content-type</parameter> is <literal>application/x-danga-s2-layer</literal>,
    you will find S2 source in the response body. As with error responses,
    you should consider only ASCII 10 (\n) to mean newline. Disregard ASCII 13
    (\r). You may transform the returned \n characters to the local newline
    representation for output if you wish.
  </para>
</section>
<section id="&s2.idroot;csp.upload">
  <title>Upload a Layer</title>
  <para>
    This mechanism can only be used to update an existing layer. This version
    of the protocol does not allow for new layers to be created via the
    interface. The S2 application will provide some mechanism, probably
    human-oriented, to do this.
  </para>
  <para>
    Uploading is done via an HTTP PUT request. The URL is the same used to
    retrieve the given layer.
  </para>
  
<programlisting>PUT /interface/s2/1 HTTP/1.1
Host: www.livejournal.com
Content-Length: 65
Content-Type: application/x-danga-s2-layer

layerinfo "type" = "layout";
layerinfo "name" = "Upload Example";
...
</programlisting>

  <para>
    If the given layer is an acceptable replacement for the layer indicated,
    the server will respond with either <returnvalue>201 Created</returnvalue>,
    which means that the layer is accepted and has been updated on the system,
    or <returnvalue>202 Accepted</returnvalue>, indicating that the layer was
    acceptable but the system will not instantly replace the existing layer
    with it for reasons unspecified.
  </para>
  <para>
    The server can also respond with any HTTP error code. The code
    <returnvalue>500</returnvalue> is used to indicate that the server is unable
    to accept the layer. If this is due to a layer compile error, the error will
    be given in the optional part of the error response after the short and long
    error descriptions.
  </para>
  <note>
    <title>Optional Client Features</title>
    <simpara>
      A client with access to a local S2 compiler may wish to perform a
      syntax check on the layer to be uploaded first. An option to override 
      this should be provided to allow for future changes to S2 syntax 
      which may cause parse errors in older versions of the compiler.
    </simpara><simpara>
      It is not advisable for the local client to attempt the checker
      phase of compilation, as this is slow and local copies of parent
      layers will frequently become out of date with that on the server.
    </simpara>
  </note>
</section>

