<title>Design Goals</title>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Easy and flexible for beginners</para>
  <para>End users who aren't programmers should be able to have an extreme
  amount of control over their journals without ever seeing or knowing HTML,
  CSS, hex color codes, or other web geekery. The styles and themes should have
  graphical previews and graphical wizards to customize every color, option,
  and text.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>Powerful, familiar, and powerful for geeks</para>
  <para>The core of S2 is actually a programming language, with syntax and
  semantics resembling Perl/C++/Java/etc. People who do know how to program
  will be able to do anything they want, including make styles which all their
  non-geek friends will able to use, since the styles are capable of reflecting
  all their options, which the graphical wizard lets them tweak.</para>
  <para>Developers shouldn't have to write a lot of repeated or unnecessary
  code. Authors of layouts need not override all functionality, instead being
  able to fall back on the core-provided functionality.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>Security</para>
  <para>Rather than letting users program directly in C or Perl, S2 ensures
  that the resultant compiled code is both safe and fast.</para>
  <para>S2 code can't get access to anything on the host machine or do anything
  malicious.</para>
  <para>S2 code can't waste host machine resources. (CPU or memory)</para>
  <para>Untrusted S2 code can't print JavaScript to prevent people from making
  styles which read their visitor's session cookies.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>Speed</para>
  <para>Internally, S2 code is compiled into a lower level language and run
  directly when the page is loaded. Unlike S1, no parsing is necessary at run
  time. Also, S2 outputs directly to the client instead of being entirely
  buffered in memory first like S1, since S2 doesn't need to do tons of
  templating replacements at the end.</para>
  <para>Trusted code by default prints direct to the client without going
  through the HTML cleaner. Untrusted, user-created layers send all their
  output through an HTML cleaner which removes JavaScript and other potentially
  harmful markup.</para>
  <para>Popular S2 code &amp; data is cached by the webserver.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>Internationalization</para>
  <para>S1 was English-centric. If you wanted to say "1 comment" vs "2
  comments", you used the magical %%s%% which was an es when plural and nothing
  otherwise. But then of course we had to make a magical %%ies%% for "1 reply"
  vs "2 replies". This ignores languages where the plural form is entirely
  different, or there are multiple plural forms.</para>
  <para>S2 uses UTF-8 everywhere, handles plural forms correctly, and makes
  customizing text/date formats/etc all trivial.</para>
  <para>S2 makes it possible for languages to override not only the text which
  will appear in the final output, but all the property names and descriptions
  as well, so understanding English is never a requirement to customize the
  look of one's content.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>

