<title>History and Motivation</title>

<para>S2 (Style System 2) is the follow-up to LiveJournal's original templating
engine, now referred to as "S1". S1 allowed people who knew HTML to somewhat
easily re-style their journal but had a number of shortcomings:</para>

<itemizedlist>
    <listitem><para>The four views (recent ("lastn"), friends, calendar, and day)
    all had to be created independently and couldn't share any code. So if you
    wanted to make a new style you had to do it four times. The tediousness of
    this made us reluctant to add any more views to the system (such as a month
    view or single item/comments view).

        <itemizedlist>
        <listitem><simpara>Styles weren't easily customizable, and thus not
        well-suited for the majority of users. While there existed the idea of
        "color themes", they were ill-designed in that it was assumed any color
        theme should be able to plug into any style. The available colors to
        set (by the themes) and use (by the styles) were named things like
        background", "foreground", "weak accent", "text on weak accent",
        "strong accent", etc. Unfortunately, no color theme worked well with
        every layout and no layout worked well with all color theme. In S2,
        color themes are specific to the layout.</simpara></listitem>
        <listitem><simpara>Colors were the only things that were easily
        customizable. Other options required editing HTML or doing CSS, both
        things which the average user neither knows nor should
        know.</simpara></listitem></itemizedlist></para></listitem>

    <listitem><simpara>S1 didn't give style authors much flexibility, since it
    didn't offer any way to do conditional output. Instead, the system itself has
    to anticipate author needs and conditionally populate and provide certain
    template blocks, depending on whether there's, say, an entry subject or not.
    S2, on the other hand, is a full programming langauge, so authors can do
    whatever they want.</simpara></listitem>
</itemizedlist>


