<title>Behind the Scenes</title>

<section id='&s2.idroot;howworks'>
<title>How it all works, in a nutshell</title>

<para>The web application gets a request and decides what user it is for, and the type of
resource it is for.</para>

<para>The web application loads the user's style for that resource, and then
  loads each layer for that style, unless it's already loaded.  (layers are selectively
  cached)</para>

<para>The S2 system builds a <emphasis role="strong">context</emphasis> which
contains the property values set by the top-most layer for each property, as
well as a function vtable computed the same way.</para>

<para>Next the web application invokes the global <function>prop_init()</function>
function which the layout layer might've implemented.  The job of this function is to initialize
the <emphasis role="strong">constructional properties</emphasis>. Constructional properties
are properties which the web app looks at to influence its subsequent data structure population.
For example, FotoBilder examines the value
of <varname>$*gallery_max_page_size</varname> to determine how many thumbnails
to load and return for a gallery.  However, a layout wouldn't always want to directly expose this
property to the users.  What if the layout was a grid and the user wanted a page size that was a
prime number?  How do you make an even grid out of 37 pictures?  This sort of layout should ask the
user for the number of rows and columns they want, then
compute <varname>$*gallery_max_page_size</varname> in
<function>prop_init()</function> by multiplying <varname>$*rows</varname> and
<varname>$*cols</varname>.</para>

<para> The web <abbrev>app</abbrev> looks at the current context and determines
both the version number of the core layer, and values of all constructional properties.
Next, it builds an appropriate data-structure for the resource requested.  This
instantiated object is probably pretty deep, containing many instantiated
objects all hanging off it.</para>

<para>The web <abbrev>app</abbrev> invokes the entry point method (probably
called <function>-&gt;print()</function>) on the object it just instantiated.
From here, S2 code runs, printing what it wants, and invoking methods on other
objects in its huge data structure (which may also print).</para>

</section>

