<title>Layer Types</title>
<para>As previously mentioned, there are 6 layers types in S2:</para>
<programlisting><![CDATA[
  => core
    => i18nc
    => layout
      => i18n
      => theme
      => user
]]></programlisting>
<para>The hierarchy above indicates which layer types are specific to which
others. For example, any given i18n, theme, or user layer is specific to a
certain layout. You can't have a theme which works with any layout, since the
theme is tied to that layout.</para>

<para>Layouts are tied to a core, but since there's at present only 1 core
layer, a layout can pretty much be thought of as the top layer. If in the
future it becomes apparent that design mistakes were made at the core layer we
can then make a new core layer and support both. Layouts will then be able to
be written to any version of the core.</para>

<variablelist>
  <varlistentry>
    <term>Core Layer (core)</term>
    <listitem><para>The core layer defines the classes of objects which will be
    provided to the S2 code by the web application. Further, it defines the
    methods on those objects and useful global functions.</para>
    <para>Only the core layer can define builtin functions and methods, where
    the implementation isn't in S2, but implemented by the host web
    application. Users cannot create new core layers. More than likely, there
    will only be one core layer on the system. However, the core layer is
    versioned in case the web application changes drastically and needs a new
    core layer. In that case, multiple core layers can exist at the same
    time, and it's the web application's job to check the version number on
    the core layer in use and provide the right data structures to it.</para>
    <para>The core also provides basic implementations for everything, in
    case other layers don't override them. One major advantage of this is
    that it makes it extremely easy for LiveJournal to add more view types in
    the future and have them be compatible with all existing layers: since
    those layers wouldn't know how to generate a "FooPage", they'll just
    inherit the FooPage from the core. (Inheritance note)</para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
    <term>Core Internationalization Layer (i18nc)</term>
    <listitem><para>The i18nc layer overrides text properties in the core,
    translating them into a specific language. It also overrides the default
    short, medium, and long date and time formats and functions which do things
    like return ordinal numbers from cardinal numbers and map item counts onto
    their plural form.</para>
    <para>The core layer should have properties for every textual string
    likely to be used by more than one layout, to reduce work for translators.
    Because the i18nc layer overrides the core, and not specific layouts,
    all layouts can take advantage of things defined in the core and i18nc layers.</para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
    <term>Layout Layer (layout)</term>
    <listitem><para>A layout is the largest and most involved layer type
    developers will create. A layout defines the look &amp; feel of the journal
    and provides all the properties which the three child layers have access to
    modify.</para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
    <term>Layout Internationalization Layer (i18n)</term>
    <listitem><para>An i18n layer is like i18nc, but it's specific to a
    layout.</para>
    <para>If a layout introduces new textual or locale-specific
    properties/functions because it couldn't use stuff already in the core,
    an i18n layer overrides just those new items. The fact that there are two
    i18n layers is hidden from the user... they just select "Deutsch" (or
    it's selected by default automatically, based on their browser settings)
    and the system picks the i18nc and i18n layers which match the "de"
    language code for their layout and core. (their core layer is also
    automatically selected if there are more than one, based on the layout
    they choose)</para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
    <term>Theme Layer (theme)</term>
    <listitem><para>A theme layer overrides color, image, font, and sound
    properties provided in the layout (some of which the layout may simply pass
    on from the core).</para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
    <term>User Layer (user)</term>
    <listitem><para>A user layer tweaks any last properties. A graphical wizard
    on the site auto-generates this after showing the end-user all the
    available properties. Everything is incredibly simple: colors are picked
    using a color-picker widget, for example.</para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
</variablelist>
<section id='&s2.idroot;layers.caps'>
  <title>Layer Capabilities</title>
  <para>The following table summarizes what each layer type is permitted to
  do:</para>
  <informaltable frame='all'>
    <tgroup cols='7' align='center' colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
      <colspec align="left" />
      <thead>
        <row>
          <entry></entry>
          <entry>core</entry>
          <entry>i18nc</entry>
          <entry>layout</entry>
          <entry>i18n</entry>
          <entry>theme</entry>
          <entry>user</entry>
        </row>
      </thead>
      <tbody>
        <row>
          <entry>Define classes</entry>
          <entry>X</entry>
          <entry />
          <entry />
          <entry />
          <entry />
          <entry />
        </row>
        <row>
          <entry>Define <function>builtin</function> functions/methods</entry>
          <entry>X</entry>
          <entry />
          <entry />
          <entry />
          <entry />
          <entry />
        </row>

        <row>
          <entry>Define global functions</entry>
          <entry>X</entry>
          <entry />
          <entry>X</entry>
          <entry />
          <entry />
          <entry />
        </row>
        <row>
          <entry>Define class methods</entry>
          <entry>X</entry>
          <entry />
          <entry>X<footnote><para>Layouts adding methods to classes must
          prefix the method name with <function>lay_</function> to avoid future
          namespace collisions should the core layer expand.</para></footnote></entry>
          <entry />
          <entry />
          <entry />
        </row>
        <row>
          <entry>Define properties</entry>
          <entry>X</entry>
          <entry />
          <entry>X</entry>
          <entry />
          <entry />
          <entry />
        </row>
        <row>
          <entry>Expose properties to graphical wizard</entry>
          <entry />
          <entry />
          <entry>X</entry>
          <entry />
          <entry />
          <entry />
        </row>
        <row>
          <entry>Override name/description of properties</entry>
          <entry>-</entry>
          <entry>X</entry>
          <entry>X</entry>
          <entry>X</entry>
          <entry />
          <entry />
        </row>
        <row>
          <entry>Override functions/methods</entry>
          <entry>-</entry>
          <entry>X</entry>
          <entry>X</entry>
          <entry>X</entry>
          <entry>X</entry>
          <entry />
        </row>
        <row>
          <entry>Set properties</entry>
          <entry>X</entry>
          <entry>X</entry>
          <entry>X</entry>
          <entry>X</entry>
          <entry>X</entry>
          <entry>X</entry>
        </row>
      </tbody>
    </tgroup>
  </informaltable>

</section>

