<appendix id="ljp.csp.faq">
  <title>Frequently Asked Questions</title>
  <qandaset>
    <qandaentry id="ljp.csp.faq.urlitemid">
      <question><para>
      How do I calculate the protocol itemid to get the <quote>&url;</quote> itemid?</para></question>
      <answer><para>For protocol methods that return an <varname>itemid</varname>, there is another variable returned
      called <varname>anum</varname>. To calculate the public &url; itemid, use the following
      formula: <literal>(itemid * 256) + anum</literal> </para></answer></qandaentry>
    <qandaentry id="ljp.csp.faq.datalimits">
      <question><simpara>What are the limitations on post and user information data?</simpara></question>
      <answer><para>To help calculate portions of your client, here are the upper limits of client affected data:
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem><simpara>Posts: 65,535 bytes</simpara></listitem>
          <listitem><simpara>Entry Properties (Currents, such as <quote>Current Music</quote>): 255 bytes or 100 characters</simpara></listitem>
          <listitem><simpara>Entry Subjects: 255 bytes or 100 characters</simpara></listitem>
          <listitem><simpara>User Picture Keywords: 40 characters</simpara></listitem>
          <listitem><simpara>Usernames: 15 characters</simpara></listitem>
          <listitem><simpara>Name: 50 characters</simpara></listitem>
          <listitem><simpara>Webpage &url;: 255 bytes</simpara></listitem>
          <listitem><simpara>Webpage Name: 255 bytes</simpara></listitem>
          <listitem><simpara>Entry dates (&unix; epoch): 1970-01-01 &ndash; 2037-12-31</simpara></listitem>          
        </itemizedlist>
      </para></answer>
    </qandaentry>
    <qandaentry id="ljp.csp.faq.downloadpage">
      <question><simpara>I just wrote a client for &lj;.  How do I go about getting it on the Download page?</simpara></question>
      <answer>
        <simpara>The Downloads page at &ljcom; currently requires manual updates, which happen infrequently.
          Due to the large userbase which uses clients offered up via the Downloads page, we
          prefer to only add well-established clients to the page.
        </simpara>
        <simpara>
          All too often, someone will code a client and then abandon it after a certain amount of time.
          If you feel that you are willing and able to commit to maintaining and providing support for
          a client, then by all means produce one and announce it on
          &ljniftyweb;.  We recommend you create a community for the users
          of your client, so you can announce new versions and provide a forum for troubleshooting
          and user support.  Once your client has matured, it will likely be included on the
          Downloads page.  If your program has reached a point where you feel it
          should be included in the page and it has not been yet, feel free to
          drop a post to the &ljdevweb; community asking why.
        </simpara>
        <itemizedlist>
          <title>Client Listing Guidelines for the <ulink url="http://www.livejournal.com/download/">Download a Client</ulink> page</title>
          <listitem><simpara>As a minimum, clients <emphasis role="strong">must</emphasis> support the basic features of &lj;,
              such as logging in, posting new entries, editing old entries, history views, etc.</simpara></listitem>
          <listitem><simpara>Client <emphasis role="strong">must</emphasis> be mature and well-established before being listed. Having minor bugs is okay, but
              we don&apos;t want to link to clients that have the potential to mess up an account.</simpara></listitem>
          <listitem><simpara>Client <emphasis role="strong">must</emphasis> be free to use. You're welcome to create and maintain a
              client that is not free/open, we just don&apos;t want to provide free advertising for such a client.</simpara></listitem>
          <listitem><simpara>Client <emphasis role="strong">must</emphasis> be originally written for &lj;. We support the Blogger and Atom &api;s, and
              we encourage interoperational clients, but we don&apos;t want to get in the habit of listing clients for
              competitor services.</simpara></listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </answer>
    </qandaentry>
    <qandaentry id="ljp.csp.faq.userinfopage">
      <question><simpara>Why doesn&apos;t my client show up on my user info page?</simpara></question>
      <answer><simpara>Client logging was disabled because its current implementation was consuming
        far too many database resources.  It may reappear in the future, if a more efficient design
        is coded and tested.
      </simpara></answer>
    </qandaentry>
    <qandaentry id="ljp.csp.faq.checkpoints">
      <question><simpara>Is there anything I need to check for in my client or script that is usually missed?</simpara></question>
      <answer><simpara>All bots/scripts need to have a well formed user-agent. That way site administrators know
      what is causing problems and can contact the author in case they need them to make some changes,
      or if they have cause to block them. Also, please make sure you specify a <link linkend="ljp.csp.versions">version</link>.
      </simpara></answer>
    </qandaentry>
    <qandaentry id="ljp.csp.faq.encoding">
      <question><simpara>Why do I get a <quote>not a valid UTF-8 stream</quote>
      or <quote>Protocol version mismatch</quote> error?</simpara></question>
      <answer><simpara>If you send non-<acronym>ASCII</acronym> data (like international characters
      in an entry), you need to use Unicode (<acronym>UTF</acronym>-8)
      <emphasis>and</emphasis> set <link linkend="ljp.csp.versions"><varname>ver=1</varname></link> to
      be recognised as a Unicode-capable client. You cannot post an entry to a
      non-person account (a community) with international or special characters at
      all, unless you set <varname>ver=1</varname>.
      </simpara></answer>
    </qandaentry>
    <qandaentry id="ljp.csp.faq.checkpals">
      <question><simpara>Why does the checkfriends mode seem to behave strangely?</simpara></question>
      <answer><simpara>On &ljcom; the return value for <parameter>interval</parameter> is either
      120 seconds, or 36000 seconds (ten hours). The value of 120 seconds is returned if the user has a
      paid account; it is effectively <quote>disabled</quote> for free (non-paid) users.
      This was introduced because continually-polling broken clients placed unnecessary strain on the servers.
      </simpara></answer>
    </qandaentry>
    <qandaentry id="ljp.csp.faq.chalresp_case">
    <question><simpara>Why might my challenge-response authentication fail?</simpara></question>
    <answer><simpara>Ensure all MD5 hashes you generate and use are lowercase. That&apos;s the
    primary cause of verification failures. &unix; does lowercase,
    many <trademark class="registered">Windows</trademark> libraries do uppercase.
    </simpara></answer>
    </qandaentry>
    <qandaentry id="ljp.csp.faq.memories">
      <question><simpara>Is there a client &api; to interact with the Memories feature?</simpara></question>
      <answer><simpara>No, there is no Memories &api; in place.
      </simpara></answer>
    </qandaentry>
    <qandaentry id="ljp.csp.faq.ssl">
      <question><simpara>Do the client &api;s allow &ssl; authentication?</simpara></question>
      <answer><simpara>&ssl; is not supported, but challenge-response is available so there is less need.
      </simpara></answer>
    </qandaentry>
    <qandaentry id="ljp.csp.faq.xml_userdata">
      <question><simpara>If I should avoid <quote>screen-scraping</quote> user pages then what are the site-friendly alternatives?</simpara></question>
      <answer><simpara>A variety of user content in machine-readable formats is available. 
      For details see the chapter on machine-readable <link linkend="ljp.int.xml_userdata.data_formats">userdata</link>.
      </simpara></answer>
    </qandaentry>
    <qandaentry id="ljp.csp.faq.fb_client_docs">
      <question><simpara>Where can I find information on the &fb; client protocol?</simpara></question>
      <answer><simpara>For information on developing clients for &fb; installations (like &scrapbook;
      on &ljcom;), please see the <ulink url="http://www.picpix.com/doc/protocol/">&fb; Protocol Documentation</ulink>.
      </simpara></answer>
    </qandaentry>
  </qandaset>
</appendix>

<!-- 
Local Variables:
mode:sgml
sgml-parent-document: ("index.xml" "part" "appendix")
End:
 -->

