<chapter id="lj.admin.caps">
  <chapterinfo>
    <title>Capabilities Classes</title>
  </chapterinfo>
  <title>Capabilities Classes</title>
  <section id="lj.admin.caps.intro">
    <title>Introduction</title>
    <para>
      To introduce user limitations as defined on a per site basis, &lj; has implemented
      the use of <quote>capabilities</quote> &mdash; customizable limits that can be defined en-masse, or
      split between different user <quote>types</quote>.
    </para>
    <para>
      Completing the idea of <quote>per site definitions</quote>, we've implemented a system where
      capabilities can be defined in classes, and classes can either be turned <quote>on</quote> or
      <quote>off</quote> for each account.
    </para>
    <para>
      Capability classes are most effectively used when making distinctions between <quote>normal</quote>
      user accounts and <quote>privileged</quote> user accounts. For example, on &ljcom;, we make
      a distinction between <quote>normal</quote> accounts, <quote>early adopter</quote> accounts, and 
      <quote>paid</quote> accounts, (with a couple of variations on the latter) &mdash; the purpose of the 
      distinction being to give paying members a better incentive to stick around and help fund the site. 
    </para>
  </section>
  <section id="lj.admin.caps.usage">
    <title>Setting Capabilities</title>
    <para>
      <xref linkend="lj.install.ljconfig.caps" /> explains how to initially set the capability defaults, and
      how to setup capability classes that you can use to define different account types.
    </para>
    <para>
      If there comes a need where a user&apos;s account should change classes, then it is easy to administrate from
      the &uri; <filename>/admin/capedit.bml</filename>. Simply login as the system account,
      and apply (or unapply) the different classes as necessary for a specific user.
    </para>
    <formalpara><title>Setting the same capability twice</title><para>
      If two capability classes set the same capability, and an account is defined under both classes, then
      the conflicting capability values are contrasted against each other, and the optimal setting is used
      where appropriate.
    </para></formalpara>
  </section>
  <section id="lj.admin.caps.list">
    <title>Capabilities Reference</title>
    <para>
      The following is a list of capabilities that you can define per class. 
    </para>
    &lj.admin.cap_list;
  </section>
</chapter>