<chapter id="lj.admin.console">
  <title>The Administrative Console</title>
  <para>
    If &bml; pages equate to the <abbrev>GUI</abbrev>
    of &lj;, then the administrative console would be the command-line interface.
  </para> 
  <section id="lj.admin.console.intro">
    <title>Taking control of the Console</title>
    <para>
      The administrative console (or <quote>console</quote>, for the sake of brevity) is
      a text only interface to &lj; that allows you to perform certain administrative
      tasks not accessible anywhere else in your installation. The console, located at the
      &uri; <filename>/admin/console/</filename> of a working &lj; 
      installation, works very similarly to a 
      <systemitem class="osname"><acronym>DOS</acronym></systemitem> 
      or <acronym>BASH</acronym> prompt, in that it reads commands and 
      arguments separated by whitespace.
    </para>
        <formalpara><title>Inputting Commands</title><para>
      The first word inputted is the command you would like to perform. Every word after that 
      is an argument to that command, and whitespace delimits multiple arguments. If an argument
      requires a space, such as writing suspension notes, it needs to be wrapped in quotation marks.
      If an argument requires spaces <emphasis>and</emphasis> quotation marks, then the quotation marks
      can be <quote>escaped</quote> with a leading backslash, like: <userinput>\"</userinput>. If 
      an explicit backslash is required when writing an argument in quotation marks, it can be escaped
      with a leading backslash, like <userinput>\\</userinput>.</para></formalpara>
      <example id="example-lj-console_suspension">
        <title>Using the console to suspend a user</title>
        <para>
          To cover all points, here is a typical input line that suspends 
          <quote>username</quote> with a complex suspension note: 
        </para><para>
        <userinput>suspend username "Indefinite suspension \\ might become \"permanent\" \\ harassment and libel"</userinput>
        </para>
      </example>
  </section>
  
  <section id="lj.admin.console.ref">
    <title>Console Command Reference</title>
    <para>
      Arguments are defined on a per command basis, and some arguments are required for the command to work.
      If you are ever stuck, just type <userinput>help <replaceable>command</replaceable></userinput> 
      in the console for a short explanation of <replaceable>command</replaceable>. 
    </para>
    <note>
      <para>
        Included with the installation is a live reference located at the &uri;: 
        <filename>/admin/console/reference.bml</filename>
      </para>
    </note>
    &lj.admin.console.ref;
  </section>
</chapter>