<chapter id="ljp.prog-guide.i18n">

<title>Internationalization</title>

<section id="lj.customize.text.thenstrip">
<title>Removing hard-coded English text</title>

<para>Avoiding hard-coded English text in files, and removing any inside
existing files is important. There are two reasons why:</para>

<orderedlist>
<listitem>
<para>So &lj; is available for users in other languages <footnote id="ftn.setlangs"><para>
The site administrator needs to make the language available for translators and
end-users, using the <xref linkend="ljconfig.langs" /> <abbrev>config.</abbrev> variable.</para></footnote>.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>So sites like <systemitem class="domainname">DeadJournal.com</systemitem> can
customize more easily, while still running the latest code.</para></listitem>
</orderedlist>
</section>

<section id="lj.customize.text.strippingtips">
    <title>The /translate/ system - English-stripping</title>

<para><emphasis role="strong">Viewing Translation Codes</emphasis></para>

<para>
You can use the <literal>uselang</literal> &url; argument to view an individual &bml; page
in a particular language. For example:
<simplelist>
<member><uri>http://www.livejournal.com/?uselang=ru</uri></member>
<member><uri>http://www.livejournal.com/?uselang=en_GB</uri></member></simplelist></para>

<para>You can also append <literal>uselang=debug</literal> to a &bml; page
&url;, to show the string names of the text on the given page:
<uri>&siteroot;/?uselang=debug</uri></para>

<para>Strings of text on the page that are not yet translatable will be in normal English text.
From this you can see which text still needs to be <quote>English-stripped</quote>,
so it can be translated (localized).</para>

<para><emphasis role="strong">English-stripping Tips</emphasis></para>

<para>There are important points to remember when English-stripping text, which might not be obvious.</para>

<orderedlist>
<listitem>
<para>If you are English-stripping, you should
strip <emphasis role="strong">everything</emphasis>. You should not leave
parentheses, brackets, punctuation, etc. hard-coded. Some languages, like Arabic
and Japanese, use their special characters for these, and some need them treated specially.</para></listitem>
<listitem>
<para><emphasis>Never split sentences</emphasis>. You should not construct sentences from smaller bits.
It tends to confuse translators, and unnecessarily limit them in their freedom.
After all, you never know what grammatical quirks a language can have, so when
you do this, you could potentially make a grammatically-correct translation impossible.
For example: <quote>Paid user</quote> and <quote>Paid user, previously an Early
Adopter</quote> should be separate strings. Most translators are happy to
use <action>Copy</action> &amp; <action>Paste</action>, so don&apos;t worry
about increasing their workload.</para></listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Last, please <emphasis role="strong">document</emphasis> unconventional things
using the <literal>|notes=</literal> directive in your translation files.
It can confuse translators a <emphasis>lot</emphasis> when they do not know
where things go or how things are put together. For something like a string, it
is important to provide a clue to what it&apos;s for, what it does, and how it works.</para></listitem></orderedlist>
<blockquote><informalexample><para><emphasis role="strong"><literal>notes</literal> directive examples:</emphasis></para>
<simplelist>
<member><code>thislang.community|notes=Name of community you use to discuss the
translation for this language.</code></member>
<member><code>Sorry|notes=typically used to announce that the requested action can&apos;t be done.</code></member>
<member><code>Error|notes=typically used inside an H1 tag to announce an error.</code></member>
</simplelist>
</informalexample></blockquote>

</section>

</chapter>

