<chapter id="ljp.prog-guide.patches">
  <title>Patches</title>
  <itemizedlist>
    <title>Patches</title>
    <listitem><para>
      Patches sent in should be in <command>diff</command> <option>-u</option>
      (<quote>unified diff</quote>) format. The correct order for the command
      is <quote>diff oldfile newfile</quote>, <emphasis>not</emphasis>
      <quote>diff newfile oldfile</quote>. If you are adding new files use
      the <option>-N</option> option. You should not send in a patch in
      <quote>normal</quote> diff <footnote id="diffs"><para>See:
      <ulink url="http://www.gnu.org/software/diffutils/manual/html_node/Normal.html#Normal">GNU:
      Diff formats - normal</ulink>
      </para></footnote> format.
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem><para>
            Alternatively you can use <command>svn diff</command> (which
            automatically outputs a native unified diff format).
            </para></listitem>
            <listitem><para>
            You can also use the <command>cvsreport.pl</command> tool with
            the <option>-d</option> option (which automatically handles file
            comparison between your live tree and the multiple repositories
            under your <filename class="directory">cvs</filename> directory).
            </para></listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>
    Follow the other programming guidelines, such as trimming trailing
    whitespace, and using (four) spaces not tabs for indentation.
    </para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>
    Your patch should be made against the current &svn; trunk revision.
    Please see the &sixacode; website for repository links.
    </para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>
    Please test your patch before you submit it; possible exceptions to
    this are small or simple modifications, like text changes. Apply your code
    and check its functionality from different angles, like community accounts,
    while logged-in and logged-out, etc. Try to make sure that as well as doing
    what you intend it to, it does not cause unexpected results in other areas.
    </para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>
    You can submit patches by posting an entry to the &ljdevweb; community,
    on &ljcom;. You can place a keyword like [patch] in the subject line, if you wish.
    </para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>
      Don&apos;t send in patches that comment out old code.  If we want the
      old code, we&apos;ll go get it from &svn;&hellip; that&apos;s what it&apos;s for.
    </para></listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
</chapter>

