<chapter id='&s2.idroot;quickstart'>
  <title>Quick Start Guide</title>
  <subtitle>Quick Start Guide to using S2 on LiveJournal</subtitle>

  <section id='&s2.idroot;quickstart.intro'>
    <title>Getting to know S2</title>
    <section id='&s2.idroot;quickstart.intro.terms'>
      <title>Common Terms</title>
      <variablelist>
        <title>General Terms</title>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Journal View</term>
          <listitem>
            <simpara>
              A journal view is the name for the different parts of a
              LiveJournal account which a user can create or customize a layout for.
              Someone's journal itself is called the <quote>Recent</quote> view,
              meaning that it shows all of that user's recent entries. The most
              popular view is the <quote>Friends</quote> view, with which a user
              can read all of their <quote>friends'</quote> updates.
            </simpara>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Layers</term>
          <listitem>
            <simpara>
              S2 uses the concept of <quote>layers</quote> to provide different levels
              of customization - each layer in a style deals with a different aspect of the
              style, ranging from color to translation to HTML options and settings. A
              complete style is the result of putting its different layers together for use.
            </simpara>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
      <variablelist>
        <title>Style Layers</title>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Core</term>
          <listitem>
            <simpara>
              This is the foundation of all styles. The core layer
              defines all of the functions and classes available to the lower
              layers. The core layer itself is fully functional as well;
              someone could use just the core definitions for each journal view
              to create a working (yet rather bland) style. It is primarily
              just a base to work from, a guide to help form a complete style that
              helps by patching holes where necessary.
            </simpara>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Core - Internationalization</term>
          <listitem>
            <simpara>
              The core internationalization layer provides all of the text information
              to help display someone's journal in a different language. This layer,
              like the core layer, is only really a base or a guide to create new
              internationalization layers from.
            </simpara>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Layout</term>
          <listitem>
            <simpara>
              A layout layer is where the real customization starts. To draw a loose
              comparison to the old style system, a layout layer can be regarded as an
              S1 style except that the S2 layout covers each journal view, unlike the
              s1 style that only dealt with a single view. A layout layer, much like the core
              layer, defines its own set of properties that change the appearance and
              behavior of the layout.
            </simpara>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Internationalization</term>
          <listitem>
            <simpara>
              An internationalization layer provides all of the text information
              that pertains to a specific layout layer, so that users can select
              which language their journal should display in. A complete style uses
              text from both an internationalization layer and the core internationalization
              layer.
            </simpara>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Theme</term>
          <listitem>
            <simpara>
              A theme layer uses the color properties available in a layout layer to create
              a unique look for the style.
            </simpara>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>User</term>
          <listitem>
            <simpara>
              A user layer is the final layer where most people's options will be set. Few people
              will create a user layer by hand, because a user layer is mostly handled by the customization
              wizards. To draw a final comparison to the old style system, you can think of a user
              layer as the equivalent to the <guilabel>Overrides</guilabel> box for S1, except there is
              a lot less headache involved in creating a user layer.
            </simpara>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </section>
    <!-- Explain how styles are built when requested, basically
    <section id='&s2.idroot;quickstart.intro.how'>
      <title>How it works</title>
    </section>
    -->
  </section>
  
  <section id='&s2.idroot;quickstart.use'>
    <sectioninfo>
      <authorgroup>
        <author><firstname>Melissa</firstname><surname>Della</surname></author>
        <editor><firstname>Jesse</firstname><surname>Proulx</surname></editor>
      </authorgroup>
    </sectioninfo>
    <title>Using S2</title>
    <para>
      In this section, we'll go through the use of wizards. They are relatively
      self-explanatory by design, so this will only briefly take you through
      the steps.
    </para>
    <procedure><title>Choosing a Style</title>
      <step>
        <para>
          The first step is to choose a layout. For example purposes we'll use the default
          style, Generator. This should already be selected at
          the <ulink url="&siteroot;/customize/">Choose Journal Style</ulink> page,
          if you haven't done any tweaking prior to reading this guide.
        </para>
      </step>
      <step>
        <para>
          Next you can choose a theme for your layout. Themes are basically
          default sets of colors that we've chosen to help you start customizing your journal.
          You can click the <guibutton>Apply Theme</guibutton> button
          underneath a layout preview you like, to choose one. If you do not
          like any of the color themes, you can override any color by creating
          a new user layer, which we'll explain how to do next.
        </para>
      </step>
       <step>
        <para>
          You customize your journal further using
          the <ulink url="&siteroot;/customize/options.bml">Customize Journal Style</ulink> page.
          You can begin creating a custom user layer by clicking the <guibutton>Customize Selected Theme</guibutton>
          button at the bottom of the page.
        </para>
      </step>
    </procedure>
    <procedure><title>Creating a user layer</title>
      <step>
        <para>
          On the Customize Journal Style page, the <guilabel>Style</guilabel> options
          are devoted to tweaking all of the available colors from the style you've chosen.
          For brevity purposes we'll only change two colors (feel free to change more as you see fit).
        </para>
        <para>
          Assuming you've chosen the Generator style, select the <guibutton>Style</guibutton> tab shown in
          the <guilabel>Customize Your Theme</guilabel> area.  From here 
          you can click on a color to choose from a pop-up color selector, or you can enter the
          hexadecimal color code if you know it. For demonstration purposes you can just type
          <userinput>#cef5c1</userinput> for the 
          <guilabel>Page background color (and around userpics)</guilabel> option.
          Scroll down to the <guilabel>Background color for the bar below entries</guilabel> option,
          and enter the following hex code in the box:
          <userinput>#f1fded</userinput>. If you have JavaScript enabled in your browser, you'll see the
          color previews dynamically change when you click outside of the option box.
        </para>
      </step>
      <step>
        <para>
          Now that you have changed a few colors, select the <guibutton>Display</guibutton> tab,
          and scroll down to the <guilabel>Additional Options</guilabel> subsection of the <guilabel>Presentation</guilabel> section.
          Enter the value <literal>400</literal> in the <guilabel>Content area width in pixels</guilabel> box.
          </para> 
      </step>
      <step>
        <para>
          Click on the <guilabel>Text </guilabel> tab. In the <guilabel>Comments</guilabel> subsection,
          enter <literal>Post a new comment</literal> in the box labelled <guilabel>Link text to leave a comment</guilabel>.
          For the next option, <guilabel>Link text to read comments</guilabel>,
          enter <literal>A single, lonely comment // It's a party in here with # people!</literal>.
          Enter these same values for the friends view entry comment links.
        </para>
      </step>
      <step>
        <para>
          Click on the <guibutton>Save Changes</guibutton> button when you've completed the steps above. Now,
          view your journal. Notice the colors, the width, and the comment links.
        </para>
      </step>
    </procedure>  
  </section>

  <section id='&s2.idroot;quickstart.moreinfo'>
    <title>Where to go from here</title>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><xref linkend='&s2.idroot;index' /></term>
        <listitem><simpara>
          We&apos;ve produced a manual covering every topic related to using S2 on LiveJournal. As a
          matter of fact you're currently reading a chapter from the manual. To start from the beginning,
          navigate to <xref linkend='&s2.idroot;index' />.
        </simpara></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><ulink url='http://community.livejournal.com/lj_style/profile'>LJ Style Discussion</ulink></term>
        <listitem><simpara>
          <ulink url='http://community.livejournal.com/lj_style/profile'>LJ Style Discussion</ulink> is a community
          on <ulink url='http://www.livejournal.com/'>LiveJournal.com</ulink> that covers most S1 and S2 discussions.
          This community has been sanctioned by administrators of LiveJournal as an <quote>official</quote> community.
        </simpara></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><ulink url='http://community.livejournal.com/s2practice/profile'>S2 Practice Discussion</ulink></term>
        <listitem><simpara>
          <ulink url='http://community.livejournal.com/s2practice/profile'>S2 Practice Discussion</ulink> is a community
          on <ulink url='http://www.livejournal.com/'>LiveJournal.com</ulink> that deals with introducing S2 to
          members of LiveJournal's support team. The introductory text available in the community was actually used
          to write portions of this chapter.
        </simpara></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </section>

</chapter>
