<chapter id='&s2.idroot;s2onlj'>
  <title>Using S2 on LiveJournal</title>
  <section id='&s2.idroot;s2onlj.resources'>
    <title>Resources</title>
    <para><variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><ulink url="&siteroot;/customize/">Customization area</ulink></term>
          <listitem><simpara>Regular end-user destination to select layouts and corresponding themes with
            pretty graphical previews, and graphical wizard to override text/colors.</simpara></listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><ulink url="&siteroot;/customize/advanced/">Advanced area</ulink></term>
          <listitem><simpara>Create styles &amp; layers. View the S2 source and documentation page of any
            public layer, notably the core layer and all the classes, functions and properties it provides.
          </simpara></listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist></para>
  </section>
  <section id='&s2.idroot;s2onlj.layerguide'>
    <title>Layer Guidelines</title>
    <para>This section is a list of suggestions for making good layers for LiveJournal, and also forms
      the requirements for creating layers to be offered as standard by LiveJournal. You should read
      this if you're designing a LiveJournal layout, or if you're writing the code to implement
      a layout designed by someone else, or if you're just interested.</para>
    <para>It seems that most people start creation of a layout by creating a static HTML mockup of
      roughly what the layout will include. With this in mind, the guide is separated into two parts,
      the first for those creating a design, and the second for those who are implementing a design
      in S2 code. You might, of course, be both!</para>

    <section id='&s2.idroot;s2onlj.layerguide.design'>
      <title>Guidelines For Layout Designers</title>
      <para>When starting to design a layout, you should keep in mind the following points.</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <formalpara>
            <title>Beware Copyright</title>
            <para>Practically everything creative is copyrighted, from images to site designs
              to program code. If you copy or clone someone else's design or HTML, or use an
              image created by someone else, you may find yourself in a copyright lawsuit.
              Also, any style which is to be part of the LiveJournal system must be distributable
              under the GNU General Public Licence (GPL) under which the LiveJournal source
              distribution is licenced. The easiest way to keep to this is to only use your
              own work in creating a layer.</para>
          </formalpara>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <formalpara>
            <title>Design Flexibly</title>
            <para>S2 is designed to be extensible, and if you think about extensibility
              early on your will make it much easier to adapt to suit additions to LiveJournal
              later on.</para>
          </formalpara>
          <para>Some particular things to bear in mind are:
            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem><simpara>Try to allow for new view types to be added in future.
                  If you've got a list of views (Recent Entries, Friends etc) then
                  will it be easy to add more views to it later on without breaking
                  the design?</simpara></listitem>
              <listitem><simpara>Try to keep the <quote>global</quote> HTML distinct
                  from the view-specific HTML. That is, decide what is part of the
                  recent view and what will be present on all views. Try to avoid
                  the view-specific HTML depending on the global HTML if you can.</simpara></listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <formalpara>
            <title>Design for standard page elements</title>
            <para>There are certain things which users expect to find in LiveJournal
              styles. These include:
              <itemizedlist>
                <listitem><simpara>Links from the archive calendar view to see the
                    month view for each month shown.</simpara></listitem>
                <listitem><simpara>A way to easily obtain <quote>permalink</quote> for each entry
                    which can be used to link to the entry. The S2 system will provide
                    the URL for this, but you need to decide where to put it.</simpara></listitem>
                <listitem><simpara>Links on the Recent Entries and Friends views to
                    navigate to older entries and back to newer entries.</simpara></listitem>
                <listitem><simpara>Links on a day page to view the previous and next day.</simpara></listitem>
                <listitem><simpara>Links on the Archive calendar to view other years.</simpara></listitem>
                <listitem><simpara>Titles and subtitles. The system allows the user
                    to give their journal a title and a subtitle, as well as a special
                    title for their friends view. You should display at least the main
                    titles as headings, and try to include the subtitle at least on
                    the Recent Entries view.</simpara></listitem>
              </itemizedlist>
            </para>
          </formalpara>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <formalpara>
            <title>Design for Customization</title>
            <para>As you are creating your design, try to think of things that users
              might want to customize. Colors are the easiest to think of, but
              you could also provide options for margin sizes, the position of
              navigation bars and chosing classes of fonts.</para>
          </formalpara>
          <para>A gotcha with customization is that it can make it hard to incorporate
            images into a style, since colors and alignments can change. If you are
            writing a potential system layout, the system can provide dynamic image
            color changes for your style in certain cases, but try to avoid this if
            you can.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <formalpara>
            <title>Design for Internationalization</title>
            <para>If you are designing a layout you should try to allow for
              the text in your layout to be translated. A lot of commonly-used text
              is already provided by the system translated, and it will be a lot
              easier to make your style multi-lingual if you make use of the
              standard text.</para>
          </formalpara>
          <para>One example is comment links on entries. The system provides functions
            to create the comment links with text set in an internationalization layer,
            including the correct pluralization for the comment count. If you design
            such that any text could be used in your comment links (and anywhere else where
            text appears, for that matter) your layout will be easily translatable.</para>
          <para>Another thing to avoid is including text in images, as this is practically
            impossible to translate flexibly.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section id='&s2.idroot;s2onlj.layerguide.implementation'>
      <title>Guidelines For Implementors</title>
      <para>If you are a programmer writing the S2 code for an S2 layout (or, to a lesser extent,
        some other layer) then this section is for you.</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <formalpara>
            <title>Use Properties</title>
            <para>If you expose properties from your layout, the end-user will be able
              to customize these properties from a web-based GUI interface. In general,
              the more of these you have the better, but don't go overboard.</para>
          </formalpara>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem><simpara>Colors are the main customizable feature of most layouts.
                Try to allow the user to change the color of all major page elements, but
                also dynamically generate similar colors based on user-supplied properties using
                the methods of the <classname>Color</classname> class to lighten, darken,
                invert or average.</simpara></listitem>
            <listitem>
              <simpara>Font selection is supported by the core layer, but you'll
                have to explicitly state that you wish to expose these properties in your
                layout. (See documentation on properties)</simpara>
              <simpara>The core layer provides options to select a primary font family
                as well as a fallback CSS generic font family, and one or both of
                these can be ommitted. You should generate a sensible CSS font-family
                property rule or equivalent FONT FACE value from these two properties.</simpara>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <formalpara>
            <title>Let the System Help You</title>
            <para>The core layer has lots of useful default implementations of various
              page features. For example, it can generate
              links to users and form page titles and subtitles from the relevant
              user settings and translation properties. Using these defaults can save
              you a lot of work.</para>
          </formalpara>
          <para>
            The system also has several features to help layouts be expandable
            without modifying a layout at all:
            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem><simpara>You can generate a list of views by iterating over
                  the <varname>views_order</varname> member of <classname>Page</classname>,
                  and if new top-level views are added in future, or if the URL to
                  one changes, your layout will automatically reflect the change.</simpara></listitem>
              <listitem><simpara>The <quote>body</quote> of each view is separated from the
                  navigation and layout around it, so that if you make sure you
                  separate the view-specific code from the global code, new views
                  can be added in future and the default HTML generated by the core
                  layer will be used until the layout is revised to provide customized
                  output.</simpara></listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <formalpara>
            <title>Text Abstraction</title>
            <para>All text in a layout should be easily overridable either by properties
              or by functions. Functions are required when text includes a number which
              affects the grammar of a sentence, such <quote>You are viewing the 10 most recent
              entries</quote>.
            </para>
          </formalpara>
          <para>Don't break up sentences when allowing sentences to be changed, as sentence
            construction differs wildly between languages.</para>
          <para>Finally, check to see if the text you need is already provided by a function in
            the core layer, as this will not only save you effort, but also save the effort of
            anyone who tries to create internationalization layers for your layout. The core
            layer provides functions and properties which are useful in practically all layouts,
            including text for comment links and view names.</para>
        </listitem>

      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

  </section>
</chapter>
