<method name="getusertags">
<shortdes>
Retrieves a list of the user's defined tags.
</shortdes>
<des>
Retrieves a list of the user's defined tags.
</des>
<arguments><struct count="1">

&authInfo;

<key name="usejournal" count="opt">
<des>
Specify this key to get tags for another account that you have access to.  By default, gets tags for your account.
</des>
&useJournal;
</key>

</struct></arguments>

<expost>
FIXME: add example
</expost>


<!--===================[ RETURN ]==============================-->
<returns><struct count="1">

<key name="tags" count="1">
    <list count="1">
        <des>
            A list of structs for all of the returned tags.
        </des>
        <struct count="0more">
            <key name="name" count="1"><scalar><des>
                The name of the tag being returned.
            </des></scalar></key>
            <key name="security_level" count="1"><scalar><des>
                The security (visibility) of the tag being returned.  This can be one of 'public', 'private', 'friends', or 'group'.  Note that 'group' doesn't provide any information about which groups, but that can be inferred from the security breakdown elsewhere in the structure.
            </des></scalar></key>
            <key name="uses" count="opt"><scalar><des>
                If the tag has been used, returns the number of times it's been used overall.
            </des></scalar></key>
            <key name="display" count="opt"><scalar><des>
                If present and on, indicates that this tag is visible to the S2 style system.  Tags with this value set to off are still usable, they're just not exposed to S2.
            </des></scalar></key>
            <key name="security" count="opt">
                <des>
                    Shows the breakdown of use by security category.
                </des>
                <struct count="0more">
                    <key name="public" count="opt"><scalar><des>
                        The number of times this tag has been used on a public post.
                    </des></scalar></key>
                    <key name="private" count="opt"><scalar><des>
                        The number of times this tag has been used on a private post.
                    </des></scalar></key>
                    <key name="friends" count="opt"><scalar><des>
                        The number of times this tag has been used on a Friends-only post.
                    </des></scalar></key>
                    <key name="groups" count="opt">
                        <struct count="0more">
                            <des>
                                Entries in the groups structure have the key being the id of the group (id as shown in getfriendgroups mode) and the value being the number of times this tag has appeared on an entry secured to that group.
                            </des>
                        </struct>
                    </key>
                </struct>
            </key>
        </struct>
    </list>
</key>
  
</struct></returns>

<exreturn>
FIXME: add example
</exreturn>
    
</method>
