 <section id="lj.customize.text.translating">
    <title>The /translate/ system - English-stripping</title>
    
<para><emphasis role="strong">English-stripping</emphasis></para>

<para>There are important points to remember when English-stripping text, which
might not be obvious.</para>

<para>First: If you are English-stripping, you should strip <emphasis role="strong">everything</emphasis>.
You should <emphasis>not</emphasis> leave parentheses, brackets, punctuation,
etc. hard-coded. Some languages, like Arabic and Japanese, use their special
characters for these, and some need them treated specially.</para>

<para>Second: <emphasis role="strong">Never</emphasis> split sentences.
You should not construct sentences from smaller bits. It tends to confuse
translators, and unnecessarily limit them in their freedom. After all, you
never know what grammatical quirks a language can have, so when you do this,
you could potentially make a grammatically-correct translation impossible.
For example: <quote>Paid user</quote> and <quote>Paid user, previously an
Early Adopter</quote> should be separate strings. Most translators are happy to
use <action>Copy</action> &amp; <action>Paste</action>, so don&apos;t worry
about increasing their workload.</para>

<para>Third and lastly, please <emphasis role="strong">document</emphasis> unconventional
things using the <literal>|notes=</literal> directive in your translation files.
It can confuse translators a <emphasis>lot</emphasis> when they do
not know where things go or how things are put together. For something like a
string, it is important to provide a clue as to what it&apos;s for, what it
does, and how it works.</para>

<informalexample>
<simplelist>
<member>Sorry|notes=typically used to announce that the requested action can&apos;t be done.</member>
<member>thislang.community|notes=Name of community you use to discuss the translation for this language.</member>
<member>Error|notes=typically used inside an H1 tag to announce an error.</member>
<simplelist>
</informalexample>

</section>

