<chapter id="lj.install.perl_setup">
  <title>Perl</title>
  <abstract>
    <simpara>The Perl motto is <quote>There is more than one way to do it</quote>, and the three principles for any
    programmer are Laziness, Impatience, &amp; Hubris, according to the Perl manual. On top of that, Perl is
    well-suited for any purpose. Anyway, in this chapter we will briefly cover a Perl installation,
    and then we will show you which Perl modules are required for a working &lj; installation.</simpara>
  </abstract>
  <section id="lj.install.perl_setup.install">
    <title>Installing Perl</title>
    <para>
      Perl offers distributions for many operating systems, including 
      <trademark class="registered">Windows</trademark> and 
      almost all of the different <quote>flavors</quote> of &unix;. Installations
      on any of these systems should be fairly easy, as most offer a simple
      installation and setup program.
    </para>
    <para>
      The complete Perl documentation is included with every Perl install, so if
      you have any Perl specific questions, you might want to refer to the
      specific documentation first.
      <footnote id="perlfaq"><para>Consult <ulink url="http://faq.perl.org/perlfaq2.html">
      <citetitle pubwork="article">Obtaining and Learning about Perl (perlfaq2)</citetitle></ulink>
      </para></footnote>
    </para>
    <tip><title>&debian;</title>
      <simpara>If you are using &debian;, Perl should already be installed. If not, the required package is
        simply: <package>perl</package></simpara>
    </tip>
  </section>
  <section id="lj.install.perl_setup.modules">
    <title>Installing Perl Modules</title>
    <para>
      &lj; requires several Perl modules to be installed. Installing these
      modules requires a fully working perl and C development environment
      (including a C compiler and make tool).
    </para>

    <note><para>
      Some modules such as <package>GD</package> and <package>Compress::Zlib</package> 
      require certain system libraries to be pre-installed on your machine.
      Please read the author-provided <filename>README</filename> files for each module before proceeding further.  
    </para>
    <para>This may mean particular development packages need to be installed on your system, before a Perl module will install in &cpan;.
    For example, on a &debian; system, to install the optional <package>Math::BigInt::GMP</package> module,
    you should install <package>libgmp3-dev</package> first. Similarly, you may need to install the
    <quote>development</quote> packages for &mysql; and <acronym>GD</acronym> on your system,
    before attempting to install the related Perl modules. The names of these packages varies
    between &linux; distributions, but are often called <replaceable>&lt;packagename&gt;</replaceable>-dev.
    Installing binary packages of modules provided through your &linux; distribution is the easier option.</para></note>

    &lj.install.perl.module.list;

    <note><para>
    Be aware that after freshly installing <filename><replaceable>make</replaceable></filename> / <filename><replaceable>gcc</replaceable></filename>, your perl installation will not necessarily detect it. This means module installation will still fail during the &apos;make&apos; stage. You may need to invoke the &cpan; shell and run the setup routine again, to point to the location of <filename>make</filename>:</para>
    
    <para><screen><prompt>#</prompt><userinput> <command>perl <option>-MCPAN -e shell CPAN</option></command></userinput></screen>  <screen><prompt>cpan&gt;</prompt> <userinput><command>o conf <option>make</option></command> <replaceable>/usr/bin/make</replaceable></userinput></screen><screen><prompt>cpan&gt;</prompt> <userinput><command>o conf <option>commit</option></command></userinput></screen></para>
    </note>
    
    <tip>
    <para>You can find out the locations of the various tools the &cpan; setup routine (<command>o conf</command>) will ask you about by using the <command>whereis</command> command, at a command prompt. 
    For example: <screen><prompt>$</prompt> <userinput><command>whereis</command> <application>gzip</application></userinput></screen></para>
    </tip> 

    <para>
      To make sure you have the necessary modules run the included tool:
      <command>&envarljhome;/bin/checkconfig.pl</command> <option>--needed-debs --only=modules</option></para>
      <para>
      If <application>checkconfig.pl</application> does not detect all of the required modules, it
      will tell you which ones you are missing. You should install those.</para>
    
  </section>
</chapter>
<!--
Local Variables:
mode:sgml
sgml-parent-document: ("index.xml" "part" "chapter")
End:
-->

