<chapter id="lj.intro.why_use">
  <title>Why Use &lj;?</title>
  <para>
    &lj; is an open source software project, with many uses
    limited only by the imagination.  Use &lj; to start your
    own weblogging community, or just about any site with a community
    focus. You can use the features such as the support system and
    feedback technology, that comes bundled with &lj;, to run
    your own online business site.
  </para>
  <para>
    &lj; has many intra-office uses as well, with its easy
    update and polling features. Use &lj; for:
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Work journals</term>
        <listitem><para>
          Record what you&apos;re working on, or scribble notes for future reference.
        </para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Project logs</term>
        <listitem><para>
          Multiple members of a project team to record
          their work, post meeting minutes, and discuss ideas.
        </para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Announcement pages</term>
        <listitem><para>
          Recording status updates to projects or
          systems on a single page, while notifying interested users.
       </para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Discussion boards</term>
        <listitem><para>
          Brainstorming ideas or soliciting opinions
          with a group, in a persistent but non-intrusive medium.
        </para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Weblogs</term>
        <listitem><para>
          Posting links to web content of interest to a particular group.
        </para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </para>
  <para>
    There are many benefits of using &lj;:
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para>
        Enhances personal productivity by providing a convenient way to
        record notes in a searchable, web-accessible medium
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>
        Provides visibility between departments or geographically-separate offices
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>
        Encourages communication by making it easy to share thoughts and comments
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>
        Encourages people to get knowledge out of their heads and notebooks
        and into a visible, searchable, central location
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>
        Provides more powerful tools for creating and accessing content than
        are available for ad-hoc log-structured web pages
      </para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </para>
  
  <section id="lj.intro.why_use.features">
    <title>Features</title>
    <para>A &lj; installation comes with many configurable features available
      <quote>out of the box</quote>, including but not limited to:</para>
    <variablelist>
      <title>Journal related</title>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Journaling service</term>
        <listitem><simpara>&lj;&apos;s core function. Users are able to submit journal
            entries and <quote>publish</quote> them on their account&apos;s journal page.</simpara></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Community journals</term>
        <listitem><simpara>Journals that many users can post top-level entries to. This allows
            for more long-term and public discussion than comments in a user&apos;s journal.</simpara></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Friends list aggregation</term>
        <listitem><simpara>Users are able to add other users to their <quote>Friends list</quote>, which
            lets them view all journal entries from their friends in an aggregate form.</simpara></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Friends filters</term>
        <listitem><simpara>Users can view a subset of their Friends lists at any given time. 
        By setting up a filter containing all their subscribed syndicated accounts, 
        a user can use their Friends list as an online <acronym>RSS</acronym>/Atom aggregator.</simpara></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Calendar view</term>
        <listitem><simpara>Users can see a record of all of their posts in the past, and
            choose to view those posts by a specific day, month, or year (allowing easy access to old posts).</simpara></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Message boards</term>
        <listitem><simpara>Users can enable or disable commenting for individual
            entries or journals as a whole. Users can choose to allow anybody,
            registered users only, or only friends to post. Users can choose to
            <quote>screen</quote> comments &mdash; make them visible 
            only to the owner of the journal &mdash; and choose to set certain levels 
            of comments to be automatically screened until approved 
            (such as a user choosing to screen all comments by
            non-friends until they decide to approve them).</simpara></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>E-mail notification of comments</term>
        <listitem><simpara>Users can choose to receive an &email;
            notification when someone comments on one of their entries (in the user's
            personal journal or in a community journal) or replies to one of their
            comments (in the user&apos;s personal journal, a friend&apos;s journal, or a
            community journal).</simpara></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Security levels</term>
        <listitem><simpara>Users can specify who can read their journal entries.
            Entries can be public (all can read), private (only the user can read),
            protected (only the user&apos;s named <quote>friends</quote> can read), or custom. 
            Custom security allows a user to specify up to 30 subgroups of their friends who
            can read the entries.</simpara></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><acronym>RSS</acronym> and Atom feeds</term>
        <listitem><simpara>Your installation publishes all public journal content as both 
        <acronym>RSS</acronym> and Atom feeds for syndication on other sites. &lj; 
        allows users to syndicate external <acronym>RSS</acronym> and Atom feeds 
        onto &lj;, to read on users&apos; Friends page.</simpara></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
       <varlistentry>
        <term>Content in a rich variety of formats</term>
        <listitem><simpara>As well as publishing entries in <acronym>RSS</acronym>/Atom formats,
        your installation publishes various <link linkend="ljp.int.xml_userdata.data_formats">account metadata</link> in
        an &xml;-based format. These include <acronym>OPML</acronym> feeds listing subscribed
        syndicated feed accounts, an Atom feed listing userpics updated to an account,
        contact information in vCard and <acronym>FOAF</acronym> 
        format, and more.</simpara></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
        <term>Tagging</term>
        <listitem><simpara>Users can tag entries into categories, allowing browsing filtered by tag 
        or syndication of entries in &xml; format by selected tags.</simpara></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Moods</term><term>mood icons</term>
        <listitem><simpara>Each entry can be given a <quote>mood</quote>, to
            describe what the user is feeling at that time. Users can choose to add a
            <quote>mood icon</quote>, which is a small picture to depict that mood. Users can
            create their own <quote>mood icon</quote> themes for use in their journal.</simpara></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Polls</term>
        <listitem><simpara>Users can create different types of polls, to get opinions,
            information, or thoughts from readers.</simpara></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Userpics</term>
        <listitem><simpara>The ability to upload small <quote>avatars</quote> that
            represent the user throughout the site. Users can re-format (e.g. crop/resize) pictures 
            as they upload them, using the &ajax;-based 
            <quote>Userpic Factory</quote> to meet requirements.</simpara></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Personalized subdomain</term>
        <listitem><simpara>If configured, users can view their journals at
            <uri><replaceable>http://username.domain.com</replaceable></uri>, as well as
            <uri><replaceable>http://www.domain.com/users/username</replaceable></uri> and
            <uri><replaceable>http://www.domain.com/~username.</replaceable></uri>  
            Site administrators can elect to use subdomains only, on a per-site basis.</simpara></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Customizing the display of the journal page</term>
        <listitem><simpara>Users can create journal <quote>styles</quote> from scratch and have
            precise control over appearance of their journals.</simpara></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Friends of Friends feature</term>
        <listitem><simpara>Users are able to see a list of entries by
            the users who are named as a friend by their friends, but not by
            the user. Users can filter this to display entries by 
            account type(s) &mdash; personal journals, syndicated accounts, etc.</simpara></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
       <varlistentry>
        <term>E-mail posting</term>
      <listitem><simpara>Post by &email;, optionally using 
      <acronym>PGP</acronym>/<acronym>GPG</acronym>-signed keys.
      </simpara></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Downloadable clients</term>
        <listitem><simpara>Users can download a program to make journal entries
            (and perform some other actions on the site) from their computer, rather
            than from the website.</simpara></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Tell a Friend</term>
        <listitem><simpara>With one click on the <quote>read entry</quote> page, users can send an
            &email; to someone else about an entry, calling the recipient&apos;s attention to
            it.</simpara></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Export feature</term>
        <listitem><simpara>Users can download their journal month-by-month, in &xml; or
            <acronym>CSV</acronym> format.</simpara></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
    <variablelist>
      <title>Account related</title>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>User bio</term>
        <listitem><simpara>Users can provide information about themselves, which is
            displayed on a profile page that can be viewed by visitors to their journal (the
            <quote>user bio</quote>). Users can enter contact and location information (&email;,
            AIM username, Yahoo! ID, Google Talk Address, Skype ID, MSN Messenger username, Jabber address,
            city, state, country, etc) and specify the security level of that
            information (public, private, protected).</simpara></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
        <term>Site search</term>
        <listitem><simpara>Users can search by contact information &mdash; finding other
            users by &email; address, AIM username, Yahoo ID, Google Talk Address, Skype ID, MSN Messenger
            username, Jabber address etc., &mdash; to locate people on your installation.</simpara></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Interests</term>
        <listitem><simpara>Users can list up to 150 one to four-word interests in their
            user bio, which other users can search for.</simpara></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Similar interest search</term>
        <listitem><simpara>If configured, users can see a list of those users whose
            interests match most closely to their own, based on an index that weights
            both number of interests in common and rarity of interests in common.</simpara></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Popular with Friends search</term>
        <listitem><simpara>The ability to see a list of the users who
            are named most often as a friend by the user&apos;s friends, but not by the
            user.</simpara></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Domain forwarding</term>
        <listitem><simpara>Users can forward their domain/subdomain to their &lj; blog (so that, for example, 
        <uri><replaceable>http://www.example.org</replaceable></uri> would
            forward to the user&apos;s &lj; 
            at <uri>http://<replaceable>username.domain.com</replaceable></uri>)</simpara></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Journal embedding</term>
        <listitem><simpara>Users can <quote>embed</quote> their journal into their home pages,
            displaying their journal as part of an external home page. (This is
            different from domain forwarding; with domain forwarding, the content is
            served from the &lj; installation; with embedding, the content is first pulled
            onto the user&apos;s server and then re-presented.)</simpara></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Text messaging</term>
        <listitem><simpara>Users can specify their text message information and
            display an option on their user bio page to allow others to text message
            them. (This allows users to receive text messages without having to make
            their information public.)</simpara></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Memory list</term>
        <listitem><simpara>Users can mark any post on the service as a <quote>memory</quote> &mdash; a &lj;
            version of bookmarking. Memories can be categorized with different
            keywords and security settings, so that users can more easily sort their memories.</simpara></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>To-do list</term>
        <listitem><simpara>Users can create their own <quote>to-do</quote> list &mdash; reminders of
            important things to do &mdash; and track percentage complete and progress on
            each item.</simpara></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Birthday list</term>
        <listitem><simpara>Users can see a list of all of their friends with
            an upcoming birthday (assuming the user has provided his or her birthday).</simpara></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
    <variablelist>
      <title>Site related</title>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Directory</term>
        <listitem><simpara>Users have access to the directory of users, where they
            can search by location, age, interest, etc.</simpara></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Schools Directory</term>
        <listitem><simpara>The Schools Directory lets a user search for users
            and communities associated with a specific school from around the world.</simpara></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
        <term>meme tracking</term>
        <listitem><simpara>Users can view a list of &url;s that have been most
            referenced in journal entries site-wide. Users can also check to see where
            those &url;s are being referenced. (By some slight alteration, users can
            also see if anyone on your installation is linking to a specific &url;, and where.)</simpara></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Random feature</term>
        <listitem><simpara>Users can view a random journal from a subset of users who
            have updated in the past 24 hours.</simpara></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
        <term>Notification of Events and Updates (<quote>&esn;</quote>)</term>
        <listitem><simpara>Users can subscribe to events like when an entry is updated or receives new comments. 
        Users can opt to receive notifications by &email; or in an on-site message center when the event occurs.</simpara></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>&openid; Support</term>
        <listitem><simpara>&openid; integration allowing commenting by users of other systems.</simpara></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Recent Comments Browser</term>
        <listitem><simpara>Users can browse recently posted comments posted by or to them, in one central place.</simpara></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Portal</term>
        <listitem><simpara>Users can use a more complex update page, which includes <quote>boxes</quote>
            of several other features, such as statistics and birthdays, on the same
            page as the update page.</simpara></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </section>
</chapter>
<!-- 
Local Variables:
mode:sgml
sgml-parent-document: ("index.xml" "part" "chapter")
End:
 -->

