<chapter id="ljp.int.statusvis">

<title>Statusvis Codes</title>

<subtitle>Status Visibility Types</subtitle>

<para><quote>statusvis</quote> stands for <quote>status visibility</quote>
and is the basic way that accounts are marked with various statuses. 
This column in the user table is a single character and is taken from the list below:</para>

<variablelist>

<varlistentry><term>V - visible</term>
<listitem>
<para>This is the normal status that applies to most accounts.  Nothing special.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry><term>S - suspended</term>
<listitem>
<para>Accounts that are suspended are effectively invisible.  Normal people
cannot see the contents of suspended journals.  People with the <quote>canview</quote>
privilege have some access to see these accounts.  (See information on that
privilege.)</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry><term>D - deleted</term>
<listitem>
<para>When someone deletes their own account.  Has much the same effects as being
suspended, except the user is allowed to undelete their account.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry><term>X - expunged</term>
<listitem>
<para>After an account has been deleted for a while it is expunged.  This process
removes all data for an account.  At this point the account can no longer
be undeleted.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry><term>R - renamed</term>
<listitem>
<para>When a user is renamed a row is created in the user table with their <emphasis role="strong">old</emphasis>
username and a statusvis of R.  This means that any requests for this user
need to be mapped to the username they renamed to.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry><term>M - memorial</term>
<listitem>
<para>No changes from a normal account except that memorial accounts cannot have
new posts added to them.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry><term>L - locked</term>
<listitem>
<para>Accounts in this status are frozen.  They cannot be logged in to, cannot
receive comments or post comments, cannot post entries, cannot edit
entries, and basically cannot do anything on the site with this account.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

</variablelist>

</chapter>

